Guide to the Paul Eno photograph collection circa 1890-circa 1955
Montana Historical Society
Paul Eno photograph collection
circa 1890 - circa 1960
circa 1905-circa 1955
Montana Historical Society Photograph Archives
Lot 025
Eno, Paul
3 boxes
191 b&w photographic prints
145 b&w film negatives
2 b&w glass plate negatives
This collection consists of images acquired from the Mai Wah Noodle Parlor and Wai Chong Tai Company buildings in Butte, Montana. Approximately half of the images in this collection document the Chinese American presence in Butte, Montana, from the early 1900’s through the 1950’s. The bulk of these images are views of Chinese businesses and snapshots of groups and individuals. They include views of Huie Pock’s mercantile and other Chinese-owned businesses in Butte, portraits of Chinese families, and snapshots of other groups and individuals. The other half of the collection consists of film negatives of the Rev. Martin D. Hudtloff family in Montana and Washington State, circa 1915-1925.
Chinese Americans in Butte
Chinese immigrants first came to Butte, Montana, in great numbers in the late 1860’s, attracted by work in placer gold mines and later by railroad construction projects. By the late 1880’s, nearly 2,500 Chinese Americans reportedly resided in Butte, and by the early 1900’s, Butte’s Chinatown had become well-established. As the gold mining boom ended and the railroads were completed, Butte’s Chinese were forced out of their jobs by discriminatory laws and ordinances meant to discourage cheap labor. In addition, the 1882 Chinese Exclusion Act barred Chinese laborers from immigrating to the United States. By the 1890’s, Butte’s Chinese residents were turning to work in the service industry.
One of the first Chinese districts in Butte arose in the Galena-Mercury neighborhood between Colorado and Arizona streets. Here, Dr. Huie Pock practiced Eastern medicine and ran a mercantile, while numerous other Chinese Americans operated general stores, laundries, noodle parlors, and herb shops. The early Chinese in Butte held onto much of their cultural heritage. They built places of worship, and many retained the dress and traditions of their homeland. In addition, they embraced some new world institutions, such as the Chinese Baptist Mission, established on Mercury Street in 1892. Some Chinese businesses thrived during this period despite growing hostile sentiment toward Chinese immigrants. However, during the first quarter of the 20th century, the Chinese population in Butte began to decline as Chinese Americans sought work in larger cities like San Francisco with flourishing Chinatowns.
By the early 1940’s, the population of Chinese in Butte had dwindled to just a few families. One of these families was the Chinn family. Albert (Yu Fong) Chinn had immigrated to America by 1912, settling in Butte with his wife, Lou, and daughter, Katherine. Albert became a merchant and by 1930 he had fathered nine children. He lived with his family at 21 West Mercury St. The Chinn family retained ownership of what are today two of the last remaining and best-preserved buildings of Butte’s Chinatown: the Wai Chong Tai Company building (15 West Mercury) and the Mai Wah Noodle Parlor building (17 West Mercury). William Chinn, a son of Albert Chinn, owned the buildings in the 1940’s, and rented the ground floor of 17 West Mercury to Paul Eno. Eno ran a lock and repair shop out of the building from late 1940’s until his death in 1986. His parents were Martha and Edgar Eno.
Martin D. Hudtloff family
Martha Eno and her family, the Hudtloff’s, moved to Butte from Wisconsin in the early 1890’s. Martha married Edgar Eno in 1901, and the couple had five children: Paul, Edward, Florentine, William, and Helen. Upon Edgar’s death in 1946, Martha moved to Vancouver, WA, to live with her son, Edward.
Martha’s brother was Martin D. Hudtloff. In 1893, Hudtloff began serving as pastor of the new St. Mark German Lutheran Church in Butte, a position he would hold for over 40 years. The congregation laid the cornerstone for their present church at the corner of Silver and Montana streets in June 1907. Martin was married to Julia Detloff, the daughter of Prussian immigrants William and Wilhelmina Detloff. Martin and Julia had five children: Walter W. G. (1894-1916), Arthur G. (1895-1968), Esther H. (1898-1950), Dorothy (1900-1908), and Martin J. (1902-1969). Dorothy died of spinal meningitis at age seven, and Walter died of a lingering illness at 22.
Arthur G. Hudtloff attended a year at the University of Montana (1914-1915). By 1916, he had moved to Seattle to study at the University of Washington, and was residing next to the campus at 4339 11th Ave NE. After graduation, Arthur served for some time in the U.S. Navy, and rose to at least the rank of Lieutenant, Junior Grade. He later moved to Tacoma, Washington, where he became the first superintendent of schools in the Clover Park School District in Lakewood, Washington. A middle school in Lakewood, Washington, a suburb of Tacoma, now bears his name.
Esther Hudtloff married Lloyd Sowders and settled in Detroit.
Martin J. Hudtloff graduated from the University of Montana and moved to Washington, D.C., where he served as Director of the Transportation Service Division for the U.S. Department of Agriculture. Martin died in 1969 and is buried at Arlington National Cemetery.
Julia’s mother, Wilhelmina Detloff, lived with the Hudtloff’s in Butte after her husband William died, and later settled in Spokane, Washington, with her nephew, George Detloff, and his family.
This collection consists of images that Hal Waldrup retrieved from the Mai Wah Noodle Parlor and Wai Chong Tai Company buildings in Butte, Montana. The photographs were collected by Paul Eno and about half document the Chinese American presence in Butte from the early 1900’s through the 1950’s. The bulk of these images are views of Chinese businesses and snapshots of groups and individuals. They include views of Huie Pock’s mercantile and other Chinese-owned businesses in Butte, portraits of Chinese families, including the Chinn family, and snapshots of other groups and individuals; most are unidentified. About half of these photographs are of an unidentified Chinese American man posed at locations in and around Butte, Montana.
The other half of the collection consists of film negatives of the Rev. Martin D. Hudtloff family in Montana and Washington State, circa 1915-1925. These include portraits of the family, many views of a family visit to Yellowstone National Park (ca. 1925), Arthur at the University of Washington and his service in the Navy, Esther Hudtloff with friends, and the George Detloff family in Spokane, Washington.
The photographs are arranged into three subgroups
Copy prints were made of all the vintage negatives.
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition information available upon request.
This collection is indexed under the following headings. Researchers desiring materials about related topics, persons, or places should search under these terms.
Huie, Pock; Hudtloff, Martin D.; Hudtloff, Julia; Hudtloff, Arthur G.; Hudtloff, Martin J.; Hudtloff, Esther H.; Detloff, George; Detloff, Wilhelmina
University of Washington
Chinese Americans -- Montana -- Butte; Chinese American businesspeople -- Montana -- Butte; Navies -- Officers; Church buildings -- Montana -- Butte
Butte (Mont.); Chinatown (Butte, Mont.); Puget Sound (Wash.); Seattle (Wash.)
Thomson's Studio; Elite Studio; Angelo (Butte, Mont.); Gibson Studio; Dusseau & Thomson; Schoettner (Butte, Mont.); H. D. Weenink; W. F. Song (San Francisco, Calif.); Lai Yung
Montana; Chinese Americans; German Americans
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Chinese Americans in Butte, Subgroup I
  - Huie Pock, Series I
    - Portrait of Huie Pock (October 15, 1914, by Thomson’s Studio, Butte, Mont.); interior and exterior views of Huie Pock’s medical office and mercantile (ca. 1908-1910), two include his son, Quong Pock Huie; large group portrait of men and women, including Huie Pock, in front of First Presbyterian Church in Butte (by Elite Studio, Butte, Mont.)., circa 1908-1914 (Box-folder 1/1)
    - Huie Pock’s office/mercantile interior, with son Quong Pock Huie, circa 1908 (Oversized M1)
    - Sam Huie’s Tailor Shop interior, circa 1908 (Oversized M2)
    - Hum Fay’s Palace Chop House interior, circa 1910 (Oversized M3)
  - Other Chinese Businesses in Butte, Montana, Series II
    - Exterior of Mai Wah Noodles & Chop Suey Building, circa 1950 (Box-folder 1/1)
  - Chinese Individuals and Groups, Series III
    - Chinese families and groups - portraits: Albert (Yu Fong) and Lou Chinn with children, including Howard, William, Albert, Youngee, Kenneth, Edward, Susan, Katherine, and Pearl (family portraits taken ca. 1920 and ca. 1927, by Gibson Studio, Butte, Mont.); woman posing with young boy and girl and older woman; group portrait of six children in Chinese dress (Angelo, Butte, 1910); group portraits of boys and young man, and a mother with children; group of male Chinese college students with Stanford and University of California pennants (ca. 1910); portrait of young women in front of “Woolman House”; portrait of two older men (ca. 1960), circa 1910 - circa 1960 (Box-folder ½)
    - Chinese boys and men - individual portraits by Montana photographers: young boy wearing elaborate hat with tassels and young men in western suits and Chinese dress - portraits by Dusseau & Thomson (Butte, Mont.), H. D. Weenink (Dillon, Mont.) and Schoettner Studio (Butte, Mont.), undated (Box-folder 1/3)
    - Chinese boys and men - individual portraits by W. F. Song (San Francisco, CA, Lai Yung (Sappatpo, Canton) and unidentified photographers, circa 1900 - circa 1950 (Box-folder 1/4)
    - Chinese girls and women – individual portraits (most ca. 1940's): Unidentified woman holding a fan by The Palmer Studio (Butte, Mont.), hand-colored portrait of girl; young women; young woman in numerous poses; young woman seated on couch with baby; and other unidentified women, circa 1940 - circa 1950 (Box-folder 1/5)
    - Chinese individuals and groups, most unidentified (1940's and 1950's): Young women; young men in Air Force uniforms; views of young men in China (T. K. Fang, S. F. Chow, and S. H. Lin) with a small folder advertising C. H. Wong Photo Studio, Shanghai, China; close-up of snow on pine tree signed by S. H. Lin, woman and man seated on couch; young people standing at the base of roller coaster possibly at Columbia Gardens in Butte, Montana, circa 1940 - circa 1955 (Box-folder 1/6)
  - Unidentified Chinese Man, Series IV
    - Unidentified Chinese man (ca. 1940's and early 1950's) Portraits and posing with birthday meal; seated on couch and standing next to tinsel-laden Christmas tree; standing in front of entrance to Paul Eno’s shop, Butte, MT; with car in front of Paul Eno’s shop, 1951 Montana license; posed at the base of Marcus Daly’s statue and on the Montana Tech campus in Butte, circa 1940 - circa 1953 (Box-folder 2/1)
    - Unidentified Chinese man on Montana Tech campus with others (early 1950’s), circa 1953 (Box-folder 2/2)
    - Unidentified Chinese man and woman shooting rifles, fishing and picnicking with others (1950’s), circa 1950 - circa 1955 (Box-folder 2/3)
    - Unidentified Chinese men and woman fishing and hunting with others, 1953 (Box-folder 2/4)
    - Unidentified Chinese man posing with women and children (early 1950’s), circa 1950 - circa 1955 (Box-folder 2/5)
- Rev. Martin D. Hudtloff Family, Subgroup II
  - Hudtloff Family, Series I
    - Hudtloff family groups (Rev. Martin D., Julia, Arthur, Martin, J. and Esther Hudtloff and Wilhelmina Detloff); St. Mark’s Lutheran Church, Butte, Montana, circa 1915 (Box-folder 2/6)
  - Arthur G. Hudtloff, Series II
    - Portraits and views taken when Arthur was at the University of Washington (ca. 1916-1920): Portraits of Arthur and Rev. Martin D. (two taken in front of Seattle, WA, house); Arthur sitting at the old Frosh Pond and fountain on the University of Washington campus, Seattle; “Recruits Seattle” - unidentified young men in uniform; Arthur and friends in front of house at 4339 11th Ave. NE, Seattle, wearing graduation gowns; entrance to the Home Economics building (later Raitt Hall) on University of Washington campus; Arthur and woman standing in front of “U.S. Naval Aviation Detachment” building (likely at the University of Washington), circa 1916 - circa 1920 (Box-folder 2/7)
    - Arthur Hudtloff in the Navy, onboard ship: Arthur wearing Navy officer’s uniform (Lieutenant, Junior Grade); Arthur aboard ship wearing a WWI-era ensign’s uniform; posed looking through portholes and in groups with fellow officers, circa 1918 (Box-folder 2/8)
    - Navy ships and Puget Sound, Washington: Views of Navy ships and other vessels on the water; Arthur Hudtloff on dock; views of Bellingham, Washington, from the water; ships and ferries in the Sound, circa 1920 (Box-folder 2/9)
  - Esther H. Hudtloff, Series III
    - Individual portraits of Esther posing in locations outdoors; Esther posing with friends at a water pump; on porch and in snow with an unidentified young man, circa 1920 (Box-folder 2/10)
  - Martin J. Hudtloff, Series IV
    - Martin in suit and bow tie; Martin with others in front of car, circa 1920 (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Rev. Martin D. Hudtloff, Series V
    - Rev. Hudtloff posed with large group; posed with group of girls in white dresses, circa 1920 (Box-folder 2/12)
  - Yellowstone National Park and family camping, Series VI
    - The Hudtloff family at Yellowstone National Park, camping: Rev. Martin Hudtloff, Julia, Arthur, Esther, and Martin J. at Yellowstone National Park; family posed with coach in front of Mammoth Hot Springs Hotel; Old Faithful Inn; family at locations around the park including Grotto Geyser, Giant Geyser, and Castle Geyser; Martin panning in stream; family standing next to cabin; tent cabin; picnicking; and man (possibly Arthur Hudtloff) feeding a bear, circa 1925 (Box-folder 3/1)
    - Yellowstone National Park: Lake Hotel exterior; Riverside Geyser; Old Faithful Geyser; Golden Gate Falls; Lower Falls of the Grand Canyon of the Yellowstone, and bears foraging at the garbage dump, circa 1925 (Box-folder 3/2)
  - Detloff/Dettlaff Family, Series VII
    - Detloff family (likely in Spokane, Washington): family in front of car and home; home exterior; father and sons working in yard and with Arthur Hudtloff, circa 1925 (Box-folder 3/3)
  - Other, Series VIII
    - Other unidentified individuals and groups: Unidentified brothers (possibly Detloff) with two women (possibly their mother and grandmother) posing with car; large group; people driving car; young girls and women; young women in overalls; women posing under a wooden pergola, undated (Box-folder 3/4)
    - Dettlaff gravestone, church interior: Wilhelmina Dettlaff (Detloff) (1837-1924) gravestone in Hudtloff family plot; interior of unidentified church (possibly St. Mark’s Lutheran Church, Butte), undated (Box-folder 3/5)
- General, Subgroup III
  - Butte (Mont.), Series I
    - View of the exterior of the First Baptist Church, Butte; unidentified man posing in front of Paul Eno’s store at 15 West Mercury, Butte; four men sitting on the steps in front of Eno’s store; men posing with dog and car; and man standing in front of a house, undated (Box-folder 3/6)
  - Other, Series II
    - Portrait of an unidentified family (circa 1890); portrait of a young woman (circa 1890); portrait of unidentified U.S. Navy Chief Petty Officer in uniform (physical training instructor specialty mark); girl posing with dog; man in waders with woman in striped dress; teepee gas station “Bar – Lodge – Cabins – Café” at Corwin Hot Springs; unidentified abandoned mine and mill site; interior of dorm room decorated with school pendants, likely at Phillips Academy, Andover, Mass.; cigarette card for Richmond Cigarettes with portrait of “Belle Archer”, circa 1890 - circa 1950 (Box-folder 3/7)
    - Class portrait: Company 3005-44, Battalion 5, Regiment 14, U.S. Naval training station, Farragut, ID, February 7, 1944 (includes list of each man pictured in the portrait) (Oversized M4)